United Steelworkers of America (USWA) AFL-CIO-CLC, Local 8652; Records apap077
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
United Steelworkers of America AFL-CIO-CLC Local 8652 Records
1977-1989
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap077
0.2 cubic ft.
This is a repository of various records related to the United Steelworkers of America (USWA) AFL-CIO-CLC, Local 865.
Collection X
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were loaned to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, for photocopying by the United Steelworkers of America AFL-CIO-CLC, Local 8652.
Organizational Sketch
The United Steelworkers of America (USWA) AFL-CIO-CLC, Local 8652 was chartered in 1977, and was apparently the first union since the nineteenth century to represent steelworkers at the Portec Corporation, Railway Products Division, in the Rolling Mill in Troy, New York. The Rail Joint Company operated the plant before being purchased by Poor and Company, which was owned by former Rail Joint Company employee, Fred Poor, in 1929. The Troy plant was a rail joint manufacturing facility. In 1989, Portec Rail Products, Inc. closed its Troy plant and moved operations to West Virginia, thereby ending Local 8652's brief history. Additional information about Portec Corporation is available through its Web site at: http://www.portecrail.com. Accessed 7 January 2003.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes contracts from 1977 through 1989, meeting minutes from 1982, job descriptions for employees from 1980, scattered correspondence, and other materials related to union business. The closing of Portec Corporation's Troy facility is documented through the support services offered for employees by the union, a seniority list, and the shutdown agreement. The scrapbook includes photocopies of news clippings and photographs documenting union members on strike from 1986-1987 and the closing of the Portec plant in Troy.
The Hart Cluett Museum (Rensselaer County Historical Society) has records from Portec Corporation's predecessor in Troy, New York the Rail Joint Company.
For additional labor collections in the Department, see the online Labor subject guide.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized alphabetically.
Rensselaer County, New York; Labor; Unions, Labor; Rail joint bars; Plant shutdowns; Strikes and lockouts--New York (State); Troy, N.Y.; Correspondence; Administrative records; Membership lists; Minutes; Financial Records; Scrapbooks; Photographs; Clippings (information artifacts); United Steelworkers of America (USWA) AFL-CIO-CLC; Portec Corporation, Railway Products Division; Rail Joint Company; Poor and Company; Portec Rail Products, Inc.
- Arbitration Concerning Holiday Pay, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bylaws, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Contracts, 1977; 1980; 1983; 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Employee Handbook for Portec, Inc., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Grievance for William E. Sagendorf - RESTRICTED, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Must consult with an archivist before viewing this material.
- Job Descriptions, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Local Union Elections Manual, 1955; 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Memoranda, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Memoranda of Understanding on Contract, 1989; 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Minutes, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Rules and Regulations for Hourly Employees, 1980-1981; 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Scrapbook, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Seniority List, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Shutdown Agreement, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Support Services for Former Portec Employees, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)